Guide to the Propaganda Poster Collection 1914-1996
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 3: Propaganda Posters (United States),World War II, 1939-1949
  - Subseries 3.1: Food and Resource Conservation, 1939-1945
    - How To Keep Warm With Less Fuel This Winter, circa 1939-1945; English; 51 x 71 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Office of War Information. (Folder 34, Item 168)
      Government issued poster advertising different ways to prepare homes for winter in order to conserve fuel for the troops. Graphic shows a couple of mean weather-proofing a house. Near the bottom of the page is the message, "Act now...while men and materials
    - Order Coal Now!, 1943; English; 55.5 x 71 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Coal Consumers' Counsel, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 34, Item 169)
      Poster issued by the U.S. Coal Consumers' Counsel telling the public to order coal early for next winter due to the scarcity of fuel caused by the war.
    - Fuel Fights! Save Your Share, 1943; English; 51 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 34, Item 170)
      Government issued poster giving the American public seven different ways to conserve fuel during the winter and fight waste in order to help the war effort.
    - Rationing Means a Fair Share For All of Us, 1943; English; 53 x 69 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Poese. Office of Price Administration, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 35, Item 171)
      Poster graphic shows two cartoon scenes set in a butcher shop, one "without rationing" and one "with rationing." In the former, a woman is offered a single pork chop, while another customer leaves the shop laden with packages. In the latter, both women, p
    - Stamp Out Black Markets...With Your Ration Stamps, 1943; English; 52.5 x 69 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 35, Item 172)
      Government issued poster used to warn American citizens to pay no more than legal prices and use their ration stamps to eliminate black markets. Graphic shows a giant thumb squashing a small scowling green man (representing black markets) under a ration s
    - Do With Less--So They'll Have Enough!, 1943; English; 55.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 35, Item 173)
      Government issued poster used to encourage American citizens to conserve their personal resources so that troops overseas will have enough. Message at the bottom reads, "Rationing Gives You Your Fair Share." Graphic shows a smiling soldier holding up a ti
    - How To Shop With Ration Tokens, circa 1939-1945; English; 94.5 x 70.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Office of Price Administration. (Folder 35, Item 174)
      Official OPA information poster showing picture illustrations of exactly how to use ration tokens to purchase food with the reassuring phrase at the bottom: "Rationing and Price Control mean A Fair Share at A Fair Price."
    - Your Country Expects You To..., 1942; English; 51 x 72.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: War Production Board, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 36, Item 175)
      Government issued poster giving four ways for Americans to conserve material resources to be used in the war effort. Graphic shows a soldier lying down with a gun, poised to fire.
    - Scrap, 1942; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: United States Department of Agriculture. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 36, Item 176)
      Government issued poster showing the need for scrap metal donations. Graphic shows an arm ascending from behind a barn and clenching pieces of old equipment in its fist.
    - Keep Scrapping, circa 1939-1945; English; 50.5 x 70.5 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Division of Information. Office for Emergency Management, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 36, Item 177)
      Government issued poster listing needed materials for the war effort with a special emphasis on separating different types of metal.
    - I'll Carry Mine Too!, 1943; English; 56 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Valentino Sarra. Office of Defense Transportation. Division of Public Inquiries. Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 37, Item 178)
      Government issued poster reminding the audience that trucks and tires must last until victory. Graphic shows a backdrop of soldiers marching and a woman carrying parcels and groceries in the foreground. (2 copies)
    - Is Your Trip Necessary?, 1943; English; 51 x 71 cm. Sepia photography with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Office of Defense Transportation. Division of Public Inquiries. Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 37, Item 179)
      A photograph shows a crowded train filled with unhappy travelers. The poster reminds its audience that unnecessary travel interferes with the war effort. (2 copies)
    - Could This Be You?, 1945; English; 46 x 66 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Office of Defense Transportation. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 37, Item 180)
      Government issued poster composed of four cartoons, each depicting travelers with different excuses for traveling. Poster serves as a reminder that only war-related travel is appropriate. (2 copies)
    - Millions Of Troops Are On The Move., 1943; English; 56 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Montgomery Melbourne. Office of Defense Transportation. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 37, Item 181)
      Government issued poster showing a train station filled with traveling soldiers reminds citizens that transportation services should first be reserved for the military and asks the question, "Is YOUR trip necessary?"
    - Don't Burn Waste Paper, circa 1939-1945; English; 44 x 55.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Rabkin. Division of Information. Office for Emergency Management, Washington, D.C. (Folder 38, Item 182)
      Government issued poster warning American citizens to donate their waste paper to the war effort rather than burning it. Graphic shows a metal garbage can filled with burning paper materials.
    - Waste Paper Makes Containers For Blood Plasma, circa 1939-1945; English; 42.5 x 60.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Victory Waste Paper Campaign. (Folder 38, Item 183)
      Advertisement for the U.S. Victory Waste Paper Campaign showing the need for paper to make packages containing blood plasma for wounded soldiers. Graphic shows a waste basket emptying out paper and the resulting plasma box.
    - Give Your Good Books To Our Fighting Men, 1943; English; 55.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: American Library Association. American Red Cross. The U.S.O. (Folder 38, Item 184)
      Poster advertising the need to give good quality books to soldiers overseas with a special emphasis on giving away books, even those that one wants to keep. Graphic shows a stream of books being released from hands above and floating down to smiling soldi
    - Books Are Weapons In The War Of Ideas, 1942; English; 51 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: S. Broder. Division of Public Inquiry. Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 38, Item 185)
      Government issued poster with inspirational quote by President Franklin D. Roosevelt illustrating the point that books are powerful weapons. Graphic shows Nazi soldiers burning piles of books in front of a giant figure of a book that seems to be made of s
    - It'll be a Great Day!, 1944; English; 36 x 50.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Harold von Schmidt. Army Conservation Project. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 38, Item 186)
      Advertising poster for the Army Conservation Project showing a smiling man dressing in front of a mirror, being sure to use all his mismatched articles of clothing.
    - Serve...Conserve, 1943; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 38, Item 187)
      Government issued poster listing ways to conserve utilities at home in the areas of electricity, communications, water, and transportation. Small illustrations appear next to conservation suggestions.
    - What Can You Spare That They Can Wear?, circa 1941-1945; English; 56 x 71 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Sponsored by Henry J. Kaiser, national chairman of United National Clothing Collection. Office of War Information. (Folder 38, Item 188)
      Advertisement for the United National Clothing Collection for Overseas War Relief being held during the month of April. Graphic shows two children dressed in rags.
    - Use It Up-Wear It Out-Make It Do!, 1943; English; 56 x 71.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 38, Item 189)
      Government issued poster encouraging Americans to use household goods as long as possible to allow more resources for the war effort. Graphic shows a woman mending a man's jeans as he fixes a lawn mower. (2 copies)
    - Save Rubber, Check Your Tires Now, 1942; English; 72 x 101 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Division of Information, Office for Emergency Management, Washington, D.C. Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 38, Item 190)
      Government issued poster encouraging Americans to take better care of their tires in order to conserve rubber. Graphic shows soldiers flying over the road with the message, "They've got more important places to go than you!..."
  - Subseries 3.2: Financial Aid: War Bonds, 1939-1945
    - To Have and to Hold!, 1944; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Treasury. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 39, Item 191)
      Poster issued by the Official U.S. Treasury to advertise the purchasing of War Bonds. Graphic shows a soldier waving a large American flag.
    - To Have and to Hold, Buy War Bonds, 1944; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Treasury. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 39, Item 192)
      Poster issued by the Official U.S. Treasury to advertise the purchasing of War Bonds. Graphic shows the face of a little girl.
    - 85 Million Americans Hold War Bonds, 1945; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Treasury. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 39, Item 193)
      Official U.S. Treasury poster issued to advertise the purchasing of War Bonds. Graphic shows a fist full of money in front of the torch hand of the Statue of Liberty.
    - Buy War Bonds, 1942; English; 68 x 104 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: N. C. Wyeth. U.S. Government Office. (Folder 39, Item 194)
      Government issued poster advertising the need for Americans to buy war bonds. Graphic depicts Uncle Sam in the clouds waving the American flag and pointing the way for troops on the ground.
    - Don't Let That Shadow Touch Them, 1942; English; 72 x 101 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Lawrence Beall Smith. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 39, Item 195)
      Government issued poster advertising the need for Americans to buy war bonds. Graphic shows American children playing on the grass with the shadow of a Nazi symbol surrounding them.
    - Our Good Earth, 1942; English; 101 x 152 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: John Steuart Curry. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 39, Item 196)
      Government issued poster advertising the need for Americans to buy war bonds. Graphic shows a farmer and his children walking through wheat fields. Quote at the bottom reads, "Make Every Market Day Bond Day." (2 copies)
    - Now--All Together, 1945; English; 23 x 32 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Cecil Calvert Beall. U.S. Treasury, 7th War Loan. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 40, Item 197)
      Official U.S. Treasury poster advertising the 7th War Loan. Graphic taken from Associated Press photograph showing U.S. Marines at Iwo Jima holding up the American flag.
    - Come on Kids-Let's do our bit!, circa 1939-1945; English; 28 x 39 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Ken. (Folder 40, Item 198)
      Poster advertising the School Savings Service, a way for children to raise money for the war effort. Graphic shows tanks and airplanes moving over the battle field.
    - We Can...We Will...We Must!, 1942; English; 52 x 28.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Carl Paulsen. Franklin D. Roosevelt. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 40, Item 199)
      Government issued poster encouraging citizens to buy U.S. War Savings Bonds and Stamps. Included is a quote from President Franklin D. Roosevelt. Graphic shows an American flag flying in the breeze.
    - And Remember USO is a Big Part of the National War Fund, circa 1939-1945; English; 35.5 x 56 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Howard Scott. Lithography in U.S.A. (Folder 40, Item 200)
      Advertising poster for the USO, saying that it is a big part of the National War Fund as well as the United Community Campaign. Graphic shows a soldier leaning out of a window seeming to be calling out to the viewer.
    - Fire Away!, 1944; English; 51 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Georges Schreiber. 5th War Loan. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 40, Item 201)
      Government issued poster in memory of the U.S.S. Dorado to encourage citizens to buy extra bonds from 5th War Loan. Graphic shows sailors keeping watch on the decks of a U.S. Navy submarine.
    - Till We Meet Again, 1942; English; 56 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Joseph Hirsch. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 40, Item 202)
      Government issued poster encouraging American citizens to buy war bonds in support of troops overseas. Graphic shows a soldier waving farewell out of a ship porthole. (2 copies)
    - How Can You Afford Those Extra War Bonds, circa 1939-1945; English; 60.5 x 77.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 40, Item 203)
      Poster advertising the need for Americans to buy more war bonds. Graphic shows a soldier who lost a leg being welcomed home by his sweetheart. The message at the bottom reads, "Is it a sacrifice to buy bonds?"
    - Remember me? I was at Bataan, circa 1943; English; 60.5 x 77.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher:A. Brook.U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 40, Item 203.1)
      54 x 71 cm. Color. Poster promoting the purchase of war bonds. The graphic is a portrait of a soldier.
    - And WE Talk About Sacrifice, 1943; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: R. Couillard. U.S. Treasury. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 40, Item 204)
      Official U.S. Treasury poster issued to encourage American citizens to buy war bonds. Graphic shows an elderly European woman in tears seated in front of the bombed-out ruins of her home.
  - Subseries 3.3: Public Morale, 1942-1945
    - Be With Him at Every Mail Call, 1945; English; 53 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Lejaren A. Hiller. Recuiting Publicity Bureau, United States Army. (Folder 41, Item 205)
      Advertising poster for the V-Mail service to American soldiers. It is described as "private, reliable, patriotic." Graphic shows a young woman smiling as she writes a letter to her soldier overseas.
    - Reach Your Boy Overseas by V-Mail, 1942; English; 55.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Jes Wilhelm Schlaikjer. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 41, Item 206)
      Advertising poster for the V-Mail service to American soldiers. Poster advertises "the letters that travel on film", "easy to use, surest, fastest, and most patriotic." Citizens are instructed to pick up V-Mail letter forms at local post offices and stati
    - Give It Your Best!, 1942; English; 35.5 x 25 cm; 101 x 71.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Charles Coiner. Division of Information, Office for Emergency Management, Washington D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 42, Item 207)
      Poster issued by the Office for Emergency Management features the American flag in order to boost the morale of workers and increase war production. (2 copies)
    - Give 'Em Both Barrels, 1941; English; 101.5 x 76 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Jean Carlu. Division of Information, Office for Emergency Management, Washington D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 42, Item 208)
      Poster issued by the Office for Emergency Management to boost the morale of factory workers by showing the parallel between their jobs and that of the soldiers on the battle field. Graphic shows a worker with a rivet gun next to a soldier with a machine g
    - America's Answer! Production, 1942; English; 101 x 76 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Jean Carlu. Division of Information, Office for Emergency Management, Washington D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 42, Item 209)
      Poster issued by the Office for Emergency Management meant to encourage factory workers by showing that they are the answer to the problems of war. Graphic shows a large gloved hand tightening the "O" on "Production", which is shaped like a bolt.
    - America's Fishing Fleet and Men, 1943; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Koerner. Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. Government Printing Office. (Folder 43, Item 210)
      Poster issued by the Office of War Information to show that even America's fishing industry is working for the war effort. Graphic shows fishermen hauling in nets filled with fish.
    - We Have Just Begun to Fight!, 1943; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. (Folder 43, Item 211)
      Poster issued by the Office to War Information to boost public morale by listing battle sites and giving the message that America has only just begun to fight. Graphic shows a soldier leading the charge with gun in hand.
    - "Americanism is not, and never was, a matter of race or ancestry.", 1943; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Franklin D. Roosevelt. Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 43, Item 212)
      A message from the President of the United States to the people concerning negative attitudes toward those considered non-Americans because of race or ancestry. The message states clearly that "Americanism is a matter of the mind and heart" and all citize
    - Help Bring Them Back To You!, 1943; English; 55.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Francis Criss. Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 43, Item 213)
      Poster issued by the Office of War Information giving practical tips for those on the home front who want to help the war effort. Graphic shows the window of a home with a service flag hanging up and a sticker with the words "This is a V Home" printed on
    - Strong in the strength of the Lord., 1942; English; 71 x 101 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: David Stone Martin. Office of War Information. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 43, Item 214)
      Poster issued by the Office of War Information to show the relation between the soldier and the factory worker in their mutual aim to fight for the "people's cause." Graphic shows three arms thrust upward, one with a rifle, one with a large wrench, and on
    - Americans Will Always Fight For Liberty, 1943; English; 72 x 101 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Bernard Perlin. Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 43, Item 215)
      Poster issued by the Office for War Information showing the parallel between those who fought in the Revolutionary war in 1778 with those fighting in 1943. Graphic shows World War II soldiers marching past the figures of Revolutionary War heroes.
  - Subseries 3.4: Military Recruitment and Training Aids, 1939-1949
    - U.S. Marine Corps, Women's Reserve, 1943; English; 15.5 x 16.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: United States Marine Corps Induction & Recruiting Station, 208 New U.S. Court House, Portland, Oregon. (Folder 44, Item 216)
      Small recruiting pamphlet for the U.S. Marine Corps Women's Reserve, featuring details on what members will wear and learn about. Most importantly, the job of female marines was to free male marines to fight in the conflict.
    - Be A Marine...Free A Marine To Fight, 1943; English; 53 x 28 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Marine Corps, Women's Reserve. (Folder 44, Item 217)
      Recruitment poster for the U.S. Marine Corps, Women's Reserve. Graphic shows the head and shoulders of a woman in uniform.
    - Symbol of Life, 1945; English; 53 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Lejaren A. Hiller. U.S. Army Nurse Corps. Recruiting Publicity Bureau, United States Army. (Folder 44, Item 218)
      Recruitment poster for the U.S. Army Nurse Corps. Graphic shows a nurse caring for a soldier in a hospital bed.
    - Radiogram To Men Of 18 And 19.., 1942; English; 51 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U. S. Army Recruiting Publicity Bureau (Folder 44, Item 219)
      Recruitment poster for the U.S. Army. Edges have apparently been trimmed, removing some of the text. Graphic shows a soldier listening to a radiogram announcement with new enlistment privileges listed on the right.
    - Keep'Em Flying! (Small Banner), 1941; English; 30.5 x 10 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: U.S. Army Recruiting Service. (Folder 44, Item 220)
      Recruiting flyer for the U.S. Army is decorated with stars and stripes and "Please Hang Up" appears at the bottom.
    - Keep'Em Flying! (Large Banner), circa 1939-1945; English; 314.5 x 43 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: The United States Army Recruiting Service. (Folder 44, Item 221)
      Large banner cut into three pieces with the slogan, "Keep'Em Flying" printed lengthwise.
    - Keep'em Flying!, 1941; English; 50.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Cecil Calvert Beall. Jack Childs. Presented by the United States Army Recruiting Service. (Folder 44, Item 222)
      Recruitment poster for the U.S. Army featuring the famous slogan "Keep'em Flying!" as well as a poem written by Jack Childs. Graphic shows a collage of images of people employed in the U.S. Army. The images are arranged in such a way as to form a large fa
    - Join! Heed Their Appeal, circa 1939-1945; English; 50.5 x 76 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Cherry. Lithography in U.S.A. (Folder 44, Item 223)
      Red Cross recruitment poster. Graphic shows crowd of people extending their hands toward a floating red cross.
    - I Need Your Skill in a War Job!, 1943; English; 56 x 71 cm. Black and white with blue and red text at top.; Creator/Publisher: James Montgomery Flagg. Division of Public Inquiries, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 44, Item 224)
      Government issued poster recruiting workers in various trades to aid the war effort. Graphic shows Uncle Sam pointing out at the audience.
    - U.S. Army, Guardian of the Colors, 1940; English; 63 x 96 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Tom B. Woodburn. Printed by Spurgeon Tucker, New York. (Folder 44, Item 225)
      U.S. Army recruitment poster. Graphic shows four soldiers marching abreast, the two in the middle carrying the American flag and the eagle crest, the two on the outside carrying rifles.